<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The seruants dutie. Or The calling and condition of seruants Seruing for the instruction, not only of seruants, but of masters and mistresses. By Thomas Fosset, preacher of the Word of God.</title>
            <author>Fosset, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11200</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853241</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853241</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18610</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01088)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18610)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 837:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The seruants dutie. Or The calling and condition of seruants Seruing for the instruction, not only of seruants, but of masters and mistresses. By Thomas Fosset, preacher of the Word of God.</title>
                  <author>Fosset, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by G. Eld,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18610:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18610:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SERVANTS DVTIE. <hi>OR THE</hi> CALLING AND CONDITION OF SERVANTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seruing for the inſtruction, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> of Seruants, but of Maſters <hi>and Miſtreſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS FOSSET, <hi>Preacher of the</hi> Word of GOD.</p>
            <bibl>GEN. 16. 9.</bibl>
            <q>Returne to thy Dame, and humble thy ſelfe vnder her hands.</q>
            <p>LONDON. Imprinted by G. <hi>Eld.</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18610:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18610:2"/>
            <head>TO THE THRICE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY, AND WORSHIPFVL <hi>GENTLEMAN AND BOVNTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> houſ-keeper Maſter THOMAS SPEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SER of <hi>Clardon</hi> in the County of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke Eſquire</hi> Thomas Foſſet <hi>wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> the felicity of this life, and of that to <hi>come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is written of one <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> who for his great wiſdome was reputed of many to bee one of the ſeuen Sages and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Greece:</hi> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other lawes and ordinances, which hee made for the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (ouer whom hee ruled) this was one, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer was proued vnthankful for a good turne receiued ſhould bee put to death, to ſhew (as I take it) what an vnnaturall and execrable ſinne vnthankefulneſſe is, and that hee is vnworthy to liue, who is
<pb facs="tcp:18610:3"/> vngratefull and vnkind to him by whom hee liueth. Wherefore (Right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) fearing leaſt I may ſeeme to haue incurred and runne already into that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and capitall crime of vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for the good turne and kindneſſe which your worſhip beſtowed vpon me, now almoſt twenty yeeres ſince: I glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laied hold of this occaſion, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I might acknowledge, and confeſſe vnto the world, how much loue and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Iowe vnto you: howſoeuer, by reaſon of my poore and obſcure eſtate, I haue not bin able al this while to manifeſt the ſame. Moreouer I ſuppoſed that this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle peece of worke, conteyning the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and duties of ſeruants, could to no man more fitly be exhibited, then to him who is and hath beene a long time ſo great an houſe-holder, and Maſter of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeruants, many laborours and hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and had experience (no doubt) both of the good, and euill, and ſo found that true by proofe and practiſe, which wee finde written, and preſcribed in the
<pb facs="tcp:18610:3"/> ſacred and euerlaſting word of God. Wherefore (good Sir) pardon I beſeech you this my boldneſſe, whereunto neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity hath, as it were, vrged me, and let not the greatneſſe of your worſhip, and worth, deſpiſe this little and ſlender gift, but giue it leaue like an Orphan to couer and hide it ſelfe vnder the ſhadow of your excellent dignity, that it may the better creepe into the hands of them it concerneth moſt, and for whoſe ſake I wrote it: If it doe good to any, honour be to God, and thankes to your worſhip for concurring to the ſame. For all the good that I haue receiued from you, I haue in my power but one thing that I can doe, and that by Gods leaue I will. performe all the daies of my life; I will pray to God aboue, the author and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all good things, long to bleſſe, keepe, and preſerue you aliue, that you may be more and more bleſſed vpon the earth, that you may liue as you haue don along time in much peace and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and honor, and credit to your houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:18610:4"/> a great peace-maker in your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, ful of good works as <hi>Dorcas,</hi> Act. 9. 39. <hi>to cloath the naked, to feed the hungry, to comfort the comfortleſſe.</hi> That when the day of your diſſolution ſhalbe at hand, and that you muſt needs enter into the way of all the world, you may ſweetly and ioyfully in a good old age fall a ſleepe in the Lord: and all thoſe good deeds which you haue done follow you (as witneſſe of your faith) euen to the Tribunal ſeat of Chriſt, where GOD will crowne in you his own workes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips humble and poore Orator. THOMAS FOSSET <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Ladbrooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18610:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or three things (ſaith the wiſe man) the earth is<note place="margin">Pro. 30. 21</note> mooued, &amp; for the fourth it cannot ſuſtaine it ſelfe; firſt, for a ſeruant when he raigneth, &amp;c. as if he had ſayd, when a ſeruant raigneth, that is deſpiſeth his maiſters gouernment, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth his owne will, and his owne wayes, it is a thing ſo euill, and diſorderly, that it maketh the earth to be mooued, the whole houſe, yea ſomtimes the whole towne, or cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be diſquieted; many be the diſorders of ſeruants in theſe our dayes, and much is the troble, &amp; diſquietnes which commeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; and the cauſe of all is this (as I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded) that ſeruants do not know their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, neither conſider the ſtate and condition of life wherevnto they be called, In tender pitty and conſideration whereof, and hoping of the good acceptance of my late publiſhed treatiſe, of the yong man in the Goſpel (good Chriſtian Reader) I was the bolder, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger to diuulge this little treatiſe, and ſhort ſermon, which doth containe and diſcouer
<pb facs="tcp:18610:5"/> the duty, calling and condition of a ſeruant, not for any worthineſſe or excellency that is in it, but to doe good (if it may be) to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, to teach the inorant, to reprooue the ſtubborne, and to let all ſeruants ſee and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand what is required of them, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they be called and the rather for that this doctrine being ſo needful, ſo little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (to my knowledge) hath beene of late written therof: although of many good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, many good men, haue written many good bookes, ſpent many good houres, to the honour of God, and edification of his church for all which bleſſed bee the name of the Lord, from this time forth for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Foſſet</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18610:5"/>
            <head>THE CAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LING AND CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Seruants, for the <hi>inſtruction of Seruants</hi> and Maſters.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. PET. 2. 21.</bibl>
               <q>For hereunto yee are called, for Chriſt alſo ſuffered for vs, leauing vs an example that yee ſhould follow his ſteps.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Moſes</hi> to build the Tabernacle, and to make all things belonging thereunto, namely the Arke, the propitiatory or mercy-ſeat, the table, the candleſticks, and the ſnuffers:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18610:6"/> for the forme and faſhion of all theſe he gaue him this charge: <hi>See</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>that thou make all things according to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 25. 40 Hebr. 8 5</note> 
               <hi>that was ſhewed thee in the mounte;</hi> for while <hi>Moſes</hi> was in the mount with him, the Lord had ſhewed him certaine formes, imaginary formes, and ſamplers of all theſe things which he would haue him to make, expreſſing thereby both the matter whereof, and the faſhion how hee would haue them made, and here now againe. <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 40. hee putteth him in minde thereof, and chargeth him that they be all made exactly and preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to thoſe formes and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes.</p>
            <p>So wee Chriſtians in the building of our ſpiritual Tabernacles, in building of our ſaluation vpon the Rocke Ieſus Chriſt, in framing and leading our liues according to Gods holy will and his word, muſt do al things, frame out all our actions and workes according to that ſampler, which Ieſus Chriſt our Lord &amp; Maſter did ſhew vs in the mount of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary,</hi> where hee was crucified for vs, that is, according to the paſſion of Chriſt, we muſt alwaies haue the bloudy paſſion of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18610:6"/> Chriſt in our minds, as a frontlet betwixt our eyes, as a ring vpon our fingers, and as a noſegay betwixt our breaſts, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which is written in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles: <hi>My beloued is vnto me as a bundle</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1. 12.</note> 
               <hi>of myrhe, he shall lye betwixt nay breaſts.</hi> For what is the paſſion of Chriſt but a ſamplar and patterne of all piety, wherein the Lord hath deſcribed and ſet downe for vs the very Images and formes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good vertues, needfull for the leading of godly and chriſtian liues, that we may learne thereby to be perfect, as our father in heauen is perfect.<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 48.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The paſſiion of Chriſt is as a book wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wemay read many good ſweet &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable leſſons, it is a glaſſe wherein we may ſee our defects &amp; wants, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we come ſhort, of many good giftes and perſections which are required of vs, and wherein the Lord hath diſcouered vnto vs the wayes of life and the pathes of righteouſneſſe. There we may ſee and learne humility, obedience, charity, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, hatred againſt ſin, contempt of this world, and of all the ritches, pleaſures and vanities therof; there we may ſee how the eternall and naturall ſonne of God,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18610:7"/> he that was equall to the father, and ſo equall that he thought it no wrong, nor robbery, to make himſelfe equall vnto him, becauſe he was equall to him by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 6.</note> and right: how he humbled himſelfe and became obedient vnto death, euen the death of the croſſe, which was the moſt ſhameful and reprochful death of all other, and the loweſt degree of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that might be, there wee may ſee a certaine, admirable and miraculous loue wherewith he loued vs, and ſo loued vs that hee layd downe his life for vs. For greater loue then this can no man haue, then that a man dye for his freinds:<note place="margin">Iohn 15. 13</note> there we may learn patience in aduerſity, and how to ſuffer all the aflictions and miſeries of this life, to enter into heauen by many tribulations, and to contemne this world, which is altogeather ſet vpon naughtineſſe. For as a good father ſayth; the man Ieſus ſuffered and indured all the euills and aduerſities of this world that he might teach vs how they are to bee ſuffered, and hee deſpiſed and contemned all the pleaſures, yea the beſt things of this life that he might ſhew vs how they are to be contemned, that neither in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18610:7"/> one we ſhould ſeeke for our felicity, nor in the other feare aduerſity: but euer with a ſtedfaſt, and vnmoueable mind, and a good courage, go foreward to the end; our hearts alwayes there fixed where our treaſure is, ſet vppon the cheefe and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame good: but the cheifeſt leſſon that we may learne in this book is obedience: For what is it that brought the ſonne of God from heauen into the Virgine wombe, from the wombe into the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, from the manger to the croſſe, from the croſſe to the graue but obedience to do the will of his father, the wil of him that ſent him. Wherevppon the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the Pſalme, induceth and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in the ſame ſonne of God comming into the world, taking our nature vpon him, and ſpeaking to God the father thus: <hi>ſacrifices and burnt-offerings thou wouldſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 40. 6. Heb. 10. 5.</note> 
               <hi>not, but a body hast thou ordained me: then ſaid I loe I come, that I ſhould do thy will O Lord:</hi> where the holy Ghoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that the cheefeſt thing that brought Ieſus Chriſt from Heauen to earth was obedience, to apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the will of God the Father in all thinges.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18610:8"/> So his ſelf confeſſeth in the Goſpel: <hi>And as my Father gaue me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, ſo doe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 15</note> I. Wherefore ſeeing that euery action of Chriſt is our inſtruction: and as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned father ſpeaketh: not only the words of the word Ieſus Chriſt, are our docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and leſſons, but the facts and deeds of the word, are our examples al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, it followeth that the firſt and greateſt buſineſſe whereunto we are to apply our ſelues in this world is, to know the will of God, and to doe it. And as our Lord and Maſter his ſelfe hath taught vs this leſſon, ſo his ſeruants and Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 15</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> according to the wiſdome gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto them, doe vrge and preſſe the ſame: that as Chriſt obeied God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vs, ſo ought wee to obey the Lord our God in all things: yea that in God, and for God, euery one in his place &amp; calling is to obey his ſuperiors, whom the Lord hath placed ouer him: ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects muſt obey their Princes, wiues their husbands, children their parents, and ſeruants their Maſters with all feare. And to this end they lay before vs this patterne and ſampler, the ſampler that was ſhewed vs in the mount, I meane,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18610:8"/> the paſſion of Chriſt and his obedience to mooue and ſtirre vs vp thereunto, euen as <hi>Antiochus</hi> the tyrant laied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">1. Matth. 6.</note> the Elephants in the day of battaile, the red and bloudy iuice of grapes and mulberies to make them fight more fearcely and valiantly. The paſſion of Chriſt is ſuch a thing, if it be well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of, that nothing to a Chriſtian man can be ſo bitter but it may be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nothing ſo ſweete but it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed. I meane that nothing is ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull and able to withdraw a man from euill, and to ſtirre him vp to good, as is the paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. And here in this Chap. ver. 13. <hi>Peter</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth with the duty and obedience of<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 13</note> ſubiects toward their Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Submit your ſelues</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to all manner of ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it bee to the King as vnto the ſuperior, or vnto gouernors as vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſent of him for the punishment of euil doers, &amp; for the praiſe of them that do wel:</hi> for ſo is the will of God that by well doing, yee may put to ſilence the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of fooliſh men. Where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle giueth vs two reaſons why ſubiects
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18610:9"/> muſt obey them that bee in authority, firſt, for that (as hee ſaith) <hi>ſo is the will of God, God will haue it ſo, it is Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which can not bee reſiſted without ſinne.</hi> Secondly, <hi>that yee may</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>put to ſilence the ignorance of foolish men,</hi> that whereas fooliſhmen doe ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bely, and ſlander you, reporting you to bee traitors and rebels, and enemies to the ſtates and higher powers, by well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, that is, by your obedience and orderly ſubiection, yee may ſtop their mouthes, and they haue nothing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by iuſtly they may ſpeake euill of you. Indeed in the primitiue Church when the Chriſtian faith firſt beganne many newly made Chriſtians, new borne babes (as <hi>Peter</hi> calleth them) hauing<note place="margin">1. Pet 2 2</note> ſcrupulous conſciences doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they beeing now become the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of Ieſus Chriſt, and entred into ſo holy a profeſſion, might and ought to obey ſuch wicked idolatrous kings, ſuch as <hi>Nero</hi> &amp; others which ſucceeded him then were: yea many ſeruants then alſo being vnder the yoke, doubted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner, whether obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence were to bee perfourmed by them to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18610:9"/> ſuch Maſters as were not onely Infidels, but enemies alſo to Chriſt and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whether the liberty of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel did not ſet them free from the yoke of bondage, vnder which they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>O no,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) ſubmit your ſeluesto euery one that hath power &amp; authority ouer</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 13</note> 
               <hi>you,</hi> to al publike magiſtrates &amp; officers, that no man may find fault with you, or chalenge you in that behalfe. <hi>Yee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the powers that bee, are ordained of God. whoſoeuer therefore &amp;c.</hi> In which places yee may ſee and read how earneſtly theſe faithfull ſeruants of Ieſus Chriſt doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, yea charge and command ſubiects to be obedient to their Kings, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and that not for feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but for very conſcience ſake, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no leſſe paine then euerlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <p>And this to deliuer the Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from ſlander, obloquie and reproch, that it might not bee ſaid that Ieſus Chriſt came into the world, to diſſolue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and good order, and to teach men ſo to do; for he came not to diſſolue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18610:10"/> and to ſet men free from the law &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſubiection; but to fulfil all obedience and righteouſneſſe, as he ſaid to <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi> Then the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> commeth here in the 18. verſe to the obedience of<note place="margin">Mat. 3. 15</note> ſeruants towards their Maſters, becauſe many of them doubted in this behalfe what they might doe, as I ſaid before: <hi>Seruants</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be ſubiect to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 18</note> 
               <hi>withal feare,</hi> not only to the good &amp; curteous, but alſo to the froward: for this is thank-worthy if a man for conſcience toward God, indure griefe, ſuffering wrongfully, for what praiſe is it, if when yee be buffeted for your faults yee take it not patiently? But &amp; if when ye dowel ye ſuffer wrong and take it patiently, this is acceptable to God: then in the next verſe hee giueth them the reaſon why they muſt doe ſo: for hereunto yee are called, God hath called you to this, that is, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and to ſuffer. For Chriſt ſuffered for you, and for vs all much wrong, iniury and contradiction, at the hands of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and euill men: and therefore they which are the Seruants of Chriſt ought much more ſo to doe. For hee ſuffered and obeied, and did all that hee did to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18610:10"/> teach you, and to leaue you an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that you ſhould follow his ſteppes, that is, walke as hee walked, obey as he obeied, and ſuffer as hee ſuffered: <hi>Yea</hi> ſaith that diſciple whom Ieſus loued<note place="margin">1. Ioh, 2. 6</note> moſt, <hi>who alſo leaned his head in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in the ſuper-while: whoſoeuer he bee that ſaith that he abideth in him muſt walk as he walked.</hi> And in the next verſe which is the two and twentith verſe; he vrgeth the Seruants further, that for as much as Chriſt did obey and ſuffer, therefore they ought ſo to doe: and he vſeth an argument drawne <hi>a maiori ad minus,</hi> from greater to the leſſer: who did no<note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 9</note> ſin, neither was there any deceipt found in his mouth: as if hee ſhould haue ſaid, Chriſt did no ſin, was innocent and free from al ſin, and puniſhments due for ſin, <hi>Yea he is the Lamb of God which taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way al ſin,</hi> yet he for conſcience and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God vouchſafed both to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and to ſuffer: how much more then ought yee to doe the ſame, who are ſinners, and by your ſinnes haue and doe daily deſerue many plagues and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for the ſame? where note I pray you how he exhorteth ſeruants to patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18610:11"/> and obedience by the example of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt. Herevnto ye ar called, euery man hath a calling, and euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is called to ſome one thing wherein his calling doth conſiſt, as the bird to flye, the fiſh to ſwimme, and <hi>man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob) is called to trauell, and labour as the ſparkes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>flie vpwards:</hi> yea men beeing all of one and the ſame nature haue diuers callings the King to rule, the maiſter to teach, and command, &amp; the ſeruant to obey: yea the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is called to three things, to labour, to ſuffer, and to ſerue. He is called to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour two wayes, firſt in <hi>genere,</hi> generally, as hee is a man. Secondly, as he is a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, generally as he is a man, becauſe the whole life of a man in this world is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall labour, as the bird is to get his food by flying, ſo is man by labour, and by the ſweat of his browes. <hi>His dayes</hi> as<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 19</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>are as the dayes of an hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> as an hireling is hired of purpoſe to labour, ſo is euery Chriſtian man hired into the vineyard to labour continually and faithfully in his place and calling, yea<note place="margin">Mat 20. 8.</note> the time wil come in the euening when the great ſteward ſhal call the labourers and giue euery man his hire: and that we ſhal all anſwer to this Interrogatory
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18610:11"/> of his owne accuſing conſcience: how haſt thou laboured? what ſayth the preacher: all thinges are full of labour, euery calling, ſtate and condition of man. Man cannot<note place="margin">Eccle. 8.</note> vtter it, and expreſſe with wordes how painefull and labourious a thing the life of<note place="margin">Eccl 18. 6.</note> a man is, if men deale faithfully in their callings. <hi>When a man</hi> (ſayth wiſe <hi>Syrach) hath done his beſt, he muſt beginne againe, and when he thinketh to come to an end, hee must goe againe to his labour.</hi> And <hi>Iob</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compteth<note place="margin">Job 5. 7.</note> this one of the miſeries of this life that a man is borne thus to trauell. If man, ſpeaking generally, if the whole nature of man be called thus to labour, then much more this man, this particular man, which is a ſeruant. And if this ſeeme much, that a ſeruant ſhould ſpend all his time in labour and paines, let them which be Chriſtian Seruants looke vpon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and the finiſher of their faith, Ieſus Chriſt: who whereas he was the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> and heire of al thinges, the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the glory of his father, and the very Image of his ſubſtance, that is, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he was God of God, light of light, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">Heb. 1. 2.</note> God of very God: that ſame great Lord of heauen and earth, at whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18610:12"/> the pillars of Heauen doe tremble, and in reſpect of whom the ſtars are not<note place="margin">Iob. 26. 11</note> cleane, for the eaſe and ioy which was ſet before him, choſe a laborious and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<note place="margin">Pſal. 88. 15.</note> life: and (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) from his youth vpward ſuffered the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and terrors of this life, was proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and tempted as we are in all things,<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.</note> ſinne onely excepted. <hi>So that if thou bee his diſciple and ſeruant, thou muſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine that which thy Maſter choſe. There is no diſciple aboue his Maſter, no ſeruant greater then his Lord; it is well and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 24</note> 
               <hi>for the diſciple, if hee be as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is.</hi> It hath euer beene the manner of good and louing ſcholers to like of, and to affect thoſe things, which they ſaw in there Maſters, yea many times their Maſters very deformities, as it is written of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> ſcholers the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripatetickes,</hi> that becauſe their Maſter had a hooked noſe, and a crooked back, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was a glory &amp; a credit among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue the ſame markes which their Maſter had, how much more then ought we Chriſtians to loue, delight in, and to imitate the vertues, the patience and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of our Lord and Maſter Ieſus
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18610:12"/> Chriſt, at the leaſt not to diſdaine and abhor that whereof hee liked and made his choice. And therefore as he ſaid vnto the Apoſtles after hee had waſhed their feete: <hi>If I beeing your Lord and Maſter haue waſhed your feete, yee ought alſo to wash the feete one of an other, for I did it to giue you an example.</hi> So ſay I to al ſeruants that beleeue, and feare God, and make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſcience of their waies, if Chriſt being your Lord and Maſter, did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like of, but chooſe a painefull and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious life, how much more doth it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you to indure that with patience which he ſuffered with ioy, for hee did it to teach you, &amp; to giue you a ſamplar how that by wel-doing yee ſhould indeuor to fulfil al righteouſnes. Chriſt hath taught you this leſſon two waies, by his word and by his deed alſo, for he began (as S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith) <hi>facere &amp; docere,</hi> to doe and to<note place="margin">Act. 1. 1.</note> teach: to do, that thereby he might teach vs to doe, &amp; indeed that is the beſt, and the moſt powerfull kind of teaching: to teach, not with words only, but alſo with workes and deeds, ſo to ſay, and ſo to do, and they that ſo teach and inſtruct other men to righteouſneſſe ſhalbe happy and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18610:13"/> bleſſed: for as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>They</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 3.</note> 
               <hi>shal shine like ſtars in the firmament for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer.</hi> The ſecond thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a ſeruant is called, is to ſuffer, what muſt he ſuffer? al thoſe euils and iniuries which his ſeruice and ſeruitude doth bring with it, Why ſo? for hereunto he is called: and Chriſt ſuffered for vs, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs an example that wee ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his ſteppes: but what and how did he ſuffer? why ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> when he was reuiled he reuiled not againe, when hee ſuffered he threatned not, but commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all to him that iudgeth iuſtly, when he was reuiled, when they told him that he was a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and had a deuil, that hee was a glutton, and a wine-bibber, a friend of Publicans and ſinners. &amp;c. hee reuiled them not, railed not vpon them, <hi>But as a sheepe before the Shearer, ſo ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hee not his mouth, when the ſouldiers buffeted him, ſpit on him, and ſtrooke him on the head,</hi> hee threatned not to bee<note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 7</note> reuenged, but with ſilence and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hee referred, and committed all to him, to whom it doth iuſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to puniſh and take vengeance: So ſaith this bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Peter,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18610:13"/> you and all ſeruants muſt doe, if yee bee reuiled and wronged, yee muſt bee ſilent,</hi> committ and commend your cauſes and caſes, your bodies and ſoules, to your faithfull God and creator, who hath a care ouer you, and in his word hath promiſed that not one haire of your head ſhall periſh, that is, not the leaſt euill which may bee, ſhall happen vnto you without his prouidence &amp; your good, if yee be ſtill patient and expect the Lords leaſure. And here as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth teach, ſo hee doth reprooue many proud, ſtubborne and diſobedient ſeruants of this time, who in the pride of their hearts take ſcorne &amp; diſdaine that their Maſters ſhould ſpeake vnto them ſharply and roughly, &amp; much more that they ſhould giue them a blow, though they deſerue it neuer ſo much, ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary and ſtubborne fellowes forget God and themſelues, they forget where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they bee called, how and what Chriſt ſuffered for vs, and for them: that it was to giue them an example to follow him in humilitie, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, patience and obedience: they forget (I ſay) the ſamplar and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18610:14"/> which was ſhewed them in the mount. Let ſuch ſeruants read the ſtory of <hi>Agar, Saraes</hi> handmaiden and ſeruant, which <hi>Agar</hi> becauſe <hi>Sara</hi> her dame or<note place="margin">Gen. 16.</note> miſtreſſe (ſeeing her ſelfe deſpiſed in her eyes) dealt roughly with her, fled away from her in to the wilderneſſe. But the Angell of the Lord found her out, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was in miſery comforted her, and aduiſed her to returne vnto her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris and to humble her ſelfe vnto her, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thereby all ſeruants that if they be dealt with after the ſame manner, that is, hardly and roughly, yet they muſt not run away, deny and detract from their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters their ſeruice, duty, and obedience: as the maner and practiſe of many proud and ſtubborne ſeruants is to doe, who when they be weary of their ſeruice, and cannot be ſet at liberty, at their own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and deſires, then they take their heeles and runne away.</p>
            <p>To which Seruants I ſay thus: that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit their maiſters doe not well to deale hardly and euilly with them, neither can they be excuſed for ſo doing, yet if the mallice and peruerſenes of their maiſters be ſuch, they notwithſtanding being ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18610:14"/> muſt not ſhake off the yoake, ſet themſelues at liberty, and depart when they liſt, firſt becauſe they haue not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their owne ſelues, they couenanted with their maiſters, tyed and bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſerue them ſo long, and in ſuch ſort.</p>
            <p>And therefore to breake thoſe bonds, couenants and promiſes, is a thing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good, honeſt, nor lawfull by the lawes of God or men: for it is plaine, <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidia,</hi> falſhood, vnfaithfulneſſe, and euill dealing, and ſuch Seruants may be called (as the Carthaginians were) <hi>foedifragi,</hi> couenant and promiſe-breakers, ſtarters aſide, and runagates: a diſobedient and ſtubborn generation, a generation whoſe<note place="margin">Gen 16. 9.</note> heart is not ſet aright, whoſe ſpirit is not faithfull to God nor to man; and ſuch are reprooued by the words of the Angell<note place="margin">Pſal 78. 8.</note> vnto <hi>Agar</hi> Gen. 16. 9. Secondly they muſt not doe ſo, becauſe it is againſt their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I mean the calling of a ſeruant, which is (as I haue ſayd) to labour and to ſuffer; it is againſt the example of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, &amp; conſequently againſt his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will, his mind and meaning.</p>
            <p>The ſeruant that is in afliction as <hi>Agar</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18610:15"/> was, hath none ſo good, and perfect a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to helpe and relecue himſelf, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Angels counſel, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelfe vnder the hands of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and with induſtry, labor &amp; patience to get and recouer his Maſters fauor, and ſo to win his Maſter with wel-doing, with doing good for euil: and as bleſſed<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 21</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> doth counſel vs all, to ouercome euil with good. Moreouer concerning your ſufferings, and that yee are called to ſuffer: yee muſt in any wiſe looke into<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 15</note> the cauſe for which ye ſuffer, That none of you ſuffer as a malefactor, a murtherer, a theefe, or as a buſie body in other mens matters, take heed that ye ſuffer not ſo, for ſuch euill cauſes, but if any of you ſuffer as a Chriſtian, let him not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, but let him glorifie God in that behalfe: yea let him reioyce, in as much as yee are made thereby partakers of Chriſts ſufferings.</p>
            <p>In all ſuffereings men muſt looke into the cauſe for which they ſuffer, for it is not the paine or puniſhment which a man ſuffereth, but the cauſe for which he ſuffereth that deſerueth praiſe, or is thanke-worthy, for many men ſuffer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18610:15"/> many and great things: Traitors ſuffer theeues and murtherers ſuffer, and that curſed fellow which muthered, of late, the Noble <hi>French</hi> King ſuffered: but what? <hi>Digna factis?</hi> things worthy of that which they had don, theſe ſufferings are ſo farre from deſeruing pitty or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, that they ſhalbe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies againſt them, and brand them with a marke of infamy for euer, he that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth for righteouſneſſe ſake, that is, in a iuſt and good cauſe: or vniuſtly with patience is happy and bleſſed, for<note place="margin">1. Pet 4. 14</note> hee ſuffereth vpon Chriſts owne croſſe, and the ſpirit of glory and of God ſhall reſt vpon him. Wherefore let not the Chriſtian ſeruant murmur nor grudge at this ſuffering if it be laid vpon him, but let him remember that hereunto hee is called; this is a burden which the Lord hath impoſed vpon him, this is the caſe and the place, and the ſtate of life in which hee muſt ſerue the LORD his GOD, if hee will ſerue him at all, and looke for the recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,<note place="margin">Col. 3. 24</note> the reward of inheritance which is promiſed to all good and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18610:16"/>
            <p>The third thing whereunto a ſeruant is called, is to ſerue, that is, to obey and to be in ſubiection, to haue no will of his owne, nor power ouer him ſelfe, but wholly to reſeigne himſelfe to the will of his Maſter, and this is to obey; for what is obedience, but as it is defined by the learned, <hi>Spontaneum &amp; rationabite voluntatis propriae ſacrificium,</hi> a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and reaſonable ſacrificing of a mans owne will, voluntarily, freely, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſtraint: and reaſonably, that is, according to reaſon and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the obedience, and feare of God, to deny his owne will, his owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and to ſubmit himſelfe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the will of GOD, and his ſuperiours in GOD, and that is called <hi>propria voluntas,</hi> a mans owne will, which is contrary, and not ſubiect, and ſubordinate vnto the will of GOD, as <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the wiſdome<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7</note> of the fleſh, which is not, neither can bee ſubiect to the wiſdome and law of God. Heere then ſeruants may ſee and learne how they muſt ſerue and obey. They muſt bee obedient at a worde, at a call, and at a becke as the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18610:16"/> Seruants of the Centurion were: who ſaith of them, <hi>if</hi> I <hi>ſay vnto one go he goeth and to another come, he cometh, or to my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant do this, he doth it.</hi> So muſt ſeruants<note place="margin">Mat 8. 9.</note> hearken with all willingnes and alacrity of mind: they muſt ſay and doe as the lad <hi>Samuell</hi> did who ſerued vnder <hi>Eli</hi> the high prieſt in the temple of the lord: when the voyce called him <hi>Samuell, Samuell,</hi> he<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3. 5.</note> anſwered by and by, heere I am, and ranne quickly to <hi>Eli</hi> and ſayd, <hi>behold heere</hi> I <hi>am, for thou calleſt me.</hi> Where ye may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and marke his readines in hearing, and his ſpeed in going, as ſoone as hee heard himſelf called he made anſwer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, <hi>heere I am,</hi> and then hee ranne, it is not ſayd that he went, but hee ranne, this confoundeth the careleſnes, or rather the contempt of many vngodly Seruants in theſe our dayes, who will not heare when they be called, but will abide ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny calllngs', and anſwer when they liſt, and then not cheerfully, and willingly, but ſlowly, and grudgingly, and when they be diſpoſe to come, they doe not make haſt and runne as <hi>Samuell</hi> did, but they goe as though they cared not whether they went or not.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18610:17"/>
            <p>Seruants muſt performe their ſeruices, and doe their duties willingly, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, as the Apoſtle telleth the Colloſſians, and as to the Epheſians he ſaith: they muſt<note place="margin">Col. 3. 23.</note> doe all from the heart with goodwill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Lord and not men: where he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth<note place="margin">Eph. 6. 5.</note> them them the reaſon, why they muſt doe it heartily and willingly, becauſe in ſeruing their maiſters they ſerue God, alſo they ſerue the Lord Chriſt, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeruices, and duties are done to God &amp; to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, muſt be done ioyfully, for <hi>God</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth) <hi>loueth a willing and a cheerefull giuer and doer in all thinges.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor 9. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore I wiſh and exhort Seruants, as many as feare God and be deſirous to know and to doe their partes and duties, for to ſearch and read the ſcriptures, and cheefely theſe two places of the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Epheſians, and to the Coloſſians. and there they may ſee how earneſtly, and zealouſly he, yea rather the ſpirit of God by him doth mooue and ſtir vp their minds to theſe good and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an duties if they only read the places with conſideration.</p>
            <p>And heere now by this time ye may ſee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18610:17"/> who is a good ſeruant, he that laboureth, he that ſuffereth, and he that obeyeth: and and if yee ſearch the ſcriptures yee ſhall finde that the praiſe of ſuch a Seruant is much, and the reward exceeding great.</p>
            <p>What ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt to the<note place="margin">Mat. 25. 21</note> good Seruant who had laboured in his Maſters ſeruice: <hi>It is well done, thou good and faithfull Seruant, becauſe thou haſt bin faithfull in a little, I wil make thee ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ouer much, enter into thy maisters ioy,</hi> as if he had ſayd: becauſe thou haſt labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſuffered, and obeyed, therefore thy labour ſhall not be in vayne. But to the euill Seruant, that is to him that hath not labored, nor ſuffered, nor obeyed, but neglecting his maiſters wil and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, careleſly had hid his maiſters ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, what is ſayd? Caſt therefore the vnprofitable Seruant into vtter darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, there ſhallbe weeping and gnaſhing of teeth: although indeed theſe Seruants heere ſpoken of in this parable myſtically are wee Chriſtians, and hee is a good Seruant to the LORD our GOD, which laboureth in the ſeruice of God for the honour of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18610:18"/> God and his owne good, not for the bread that periſheth, but for that which<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> remaineth to life euerlaſting. Hee that ſuffereth all the afflictions and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions which a Godly and Chriſtian life bringeth with it. He that obeyeth the Goſpell, the will and the word of Ieſus Chriſt in all things, and to this Seruant it is ſaid, <hi>it is wel done thou good and faithful ſeruant &amp;c. Enter into thy Maſters ioy,</hi> into euerlaſting life, where is fulneſſe of ioy and pleaſures for euer. Now if it like you to walke abroade into the fields and paſtures of the holy Scriptures, yee ſhall find examples both of good and euill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, whereby yee may learne what to follow, and what to auoide. For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures lay before vs (as a looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſſe) both the vices and vertues of men, their vices to auoide them, their vertues to follow them, to teach vs both to decline from euill, and to doe good: vpon which two points al Chriſtian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine<note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 14</note> is grounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudas,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iſcariot,</hi> was a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, but neither good, nor faithfull, for hee was a Traitor and a Theefe, hee carried the bagge, the purſe and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued<note place="margin">Joh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 6</note>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18610:18"/> thoſe things which were giuen: yea hee dealt falſely and kept that to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe which was giuen to Ieſus his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; for the releefe of himſelfe, and of thoſe which followed him. This coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, this inordinate deſire of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, this roote of all euill, increaſing and growing in him more and more, at the length it brought him to that wicked and horrible deſignement, that hee was content for lucre ſake, to ſell and betray his Maſter, his good Maſter, euen the Lord of life, the King of glory: which when he had done, his owne conſcience became vnto him, an accuſer, a witneſſe, a iudge, and a hangman: and forthwith he<note place="margin">Act. 1. 18</note> tooke an halter and hanged himſelfe, his belly burſt, and his bowels guſhed out, and ſo he periſhed fearefully, to the great terrour and admiration, not onely of all that were then at Ieruſalem, but of all the world beſide, as many as haue or ſhall heare of it hereafter. Wherefore by his example let Seruants beware and take heed how they bee falſe, and deceiue their Maſters, let them bee true and luſt, and faithfull in all things, let them take heed of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteouſneſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18610:19"/> which is ſuch a peſtiferous and cancrous thing, eating, and creeping ſtill more and more into the heartes of men, that it conſumeth and deuoureth in them all fayth to God, and loue to men, and bringeth them to moſt wicked reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and attempts. Couetouſneſſe (ſayth an ancient father) neither feareth God nor regardeth man, neither ſpareth father, neither knoweth mother, with his brother he accordeth not, nor with his freind keepeth be truth. This made the<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.</note> Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay that the loue of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is the roote of all euill; and the wiſe man <hi>Syrach</hi> to conclude, that there is nothing worſe then a couetous man nor<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.</note> a more wicked thing then the loue of money, For (ſayth he) <hi>ſuch a man wil ſell euen his owne ſoule,</hi> not onely his friend and his maiſter as <hi>Iudas</hi> did, but his own<note place="margin">4 Reg 5.</note> ſoule alſo. Such a Seruant had <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet, and man of God, called <hi>Gehezi,</hi> who croſſed his good maiſter in that which he hated, that is, in forging of lyes and in taking gifts and bribes, when his maiſter had healed the noble man of Syria freely, and as he freely receiued the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18610:19"/> gift, ſo freely had beſtowed it for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the God of Iſrael, this fellow eſteeming a little money and rayment. more then the glory of God, and his maiſters credit, ranne after him, and by a lye obtained money and apparrell. But the Lord, to whoſe eyes al thinges are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and naked, diſcouered the fraud of<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> this ſeruant vnto his maiſter, the Prophet who reproouing him for it, the fearefull plague of Leaproſie, which hee had that was cured, was layd vppon this fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fellow, to cleaue to him, and to his ſeed for euer.</p>
            <p>Let Seruants take heed of lying, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and ſuch cunning practiſes to get vnto themſelues, without their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters knowledge, and let them ſhew all good fidelity, and faithfulneſſe, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring themſelues, that howſoeuer<note place="margin">Eccl 23. 19.</note> they may deceiue the eyes of men, for a time, yet they cannot deceiue the al ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and al-knowing God, whoſe eyes are ten thouſand times brighter then the Sunne, who will lighten the hidden<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 5.</note> thinges of darkeneſſe, and make knowne the very counſells and thoughtes of the heart.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18610:20"/>
            <p>There bee many ſeruants in theſe daies ſuch as this <hi>Gehezi</hi> was, greedie bribing companions: yea one can not come to a man of any place or faſhion to ſeeke for fauour, iuſtice, and equity but <hi>Gehezi</hi> wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and gapeth for ſomwhat, or elſe hee ſhal hardly be welcome, &amp; he may chance to ſtand without. And thus Couetouſnes and Bribery beganne to creepe into the houſes of great men, of ſuch as be in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limity, and authority, by meanes of the Seruants, but now rhe Maiſters perceiuing this practiſe &amp; gaine of the ſeruants, haue taken it into their owne handes, not that they would not haue their ſeruants couet, and take, but that they would haue them doe it for them, and not for themſelues, the maiſter his ſelfe will not bee ſeene to take any bribe, or any way to be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe theſe thinges be directly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but he wil haue one about him that ſhall take bribes, out of the boſomes of men, and put them into his maiſters poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket.</p>
            <p>By which meanes much wickedneſſe and many euills are committed, much wrong, oppreſſion, and iniuſtice, as in the dayes of <hi>Amos</hi> the Prophet, which made
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18610:20"/> him complaine againſt the Rulers &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and ſay: <hi>yee haue turned iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into gaul and the fruit of righteouſnes into wormewood,</hi> meaning, that whereas<note place="margin">Amos. 5. 7.</note> men poore and oppreſſed looked for iudgement and iuſtice, helpe and deliuery and thereby for ioy and comfort, they on the contrary fide find nothing but bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of ſoule, ſorrow and heauineſſe of heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioab</hi> one of the ſonnes of <hi>Zeruia,</hi> was a ſeruant to King <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the cheife Captaine, and gouernour of his hoſt, and Garriſons, but he was not a good ſeruant and that for two cauſes, firſt for that he dealt not ſimply and plainely with his maiſter the King, but by craft and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty practiſed to reconcile <hi>Abſolon</hi> vnto<note place="margin">2. Sa 14 2.</note> his father, for he prouided a bold and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious woman, <hi>a ſubtill woman</hi> (ſayth the text) ſuch an one as the world is full of now which can lye and diſſemble. And this woman after this <hi>Ioab</hi> had inſtructed and taught her her leſſon, commeth to the king, fayning, and counterfeiting a certaine heauineſſe, putteth a caſe to him; the King beeing a mercifull man, and one that euer pittyed the needy and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18610:21"/> diſtreſſed, ſpake ſo much and ſo comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably vnto her, that when he perceiued what her drift and meaning was, hee granted her requeſt, and aſked her whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the hand of <hi>Ioab</hi> were not in that buſineſſe: where vppon ſhe confeſſed the whole matter, how he the ſaid <hi>Ioab</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornd her to that end, that is, to worke that with the King by ſubtilty, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wherevnto hee would not haue beene brought with direct and plaine dealing.</p>
            <p>The King becauſe he had ſpoken the word was content that his inceſtuous, and rebellious ſonne ſhould be recalled from baniſhment, and come to the citty: but not admitted to his ſight, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; which fact of <hi>Ioabs</hi> the king re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring although hee were content to be ouer-ruled for the preſent: yet<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King. 2. 6</note> when the time was come that he ſhould dye, and enter into the way of all the earth, hee charged <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne, that for this, and ſome other diſpleaſures which hee had taken againſt this <hi>Ioab,</hi> that hee ſhould not ſuffer his hoary head to goe to the graue in peace, albeit that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18610:21"/> this <hi>Ioab</hi> was his old Seruant, his neere kinſman, euen his owne ſiſters ſonne. Shewing thereby that it is a great hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous offence, and almoſt not pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for a Seruant toward his Maſter, or a ſubiect toward his King to vſe any fraud and diſſimulation, and not to deale ſimply, and ſingly with them in al things. Seruants as they muſt ſerue their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in truth and fidelity, ſo muſt they<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 5.</note> doe it in ſingleneſſe of heart, as vnto Chriſt, all duplicity and double dealing, as it is euill in all men, ſo is it ſpecially in euery inferiour toward his ſuperiour, whom the Lord hath commanded him to obey voluntarily, and conſcionably, as to his owne ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly this <hi>Ioab</hi> was not a good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, for that hee did not onely conſent vnto his Maſters ſinne, but was the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and finiſher of the ſame. Fot whereas the King being poſſeſſed with the vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful loue of the wife of <hi>Vrias,</hi> and luſting after her, wrote vnto this his ſeruant <hi>Ioab</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam 11. 6.</note> to make away this innocent man, hee as ſoone as he receiued the letters, put it in execution, ſet him in the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous place of the battaile, where hee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18610:22"/> was ſure to be ſlaine: which being effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he ſent word to the King, ſaying, V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sa. 13.</note> 
               <hi>is dead,</hi> ſuch were the ſeruants of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon,</hi> euill ſeruants of an euill Maſter, as ready to worke wickedneſſe and to doe euill, as their Maſter was to command it. For when as <hi>Abſolon</hi> of a malicious and reuenging minde had bid them to ſmite, murther, and kill his brother <hi>Ammon</hi> at the table, when hee and the reſt of the Kings ſonnes were merry and full of wine: theſe ſwaggerers and hacſters made no bones at it, but did ſo in deed, boldly and bloudily they kill the ſonne of a King in the ſight and preſence of the reſt of the Kings ſonnes, and other of the nobility, then and there aſſembled: This world is full of ſuch vngodly ſeruants, <hi>whoſe feete beeing</hi> (as the Prophet ſaith) <hi>ſwift to ſhead bloud, and their right hand a right hand of iniquity,</hi> nothing can bee by their Maſters ſo abominably comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but it ſhalbe by them with ſpeed deſperately attempted, ſo muſt not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants doe, they muſt not doe euili vnder a colour and ſhew of good, I meane of pleaſing and obeying their Maſters: they muſt pleaſe and obey, but in the Lord, in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18610:22"/> all good, honeſt and lawfull things, ſo far as the Lord in his word doth will, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or giue them leaue, <hi>vſque ad Aras:</hi> and no further.</p>
            <p>All obedience muſt bee ſubordinate vnto the deuine obedience due vnto God. If thy Maſter bid thee doe euill, hurt thy neigbours cattell, or ſteale his goods; if hee command thee, or giue thee example to cogge and lie, to ſteale or vſe any fraud or deceipt in buying, or ſelling, to ſell that which is euill for good, to exact more then a thing is worth, to doe any thing which you would not bee content ſhould bee done to you: then ſay as Chriſt, the Maſter of vs all ſaid, when one told him that his mother and his brethren ſtood without<note place="margin">Mat. 12 48</note> to ſpeake with him: <hi>Who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is my mother, and who are my brethren &amp;c.</hi> And as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> anſwered to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of the Iewes, when they for-bad them to ſpeake any more in the name of Ieſus, whether it be right in ſight of God to obey you rather then God, iudge yee.<note place="margin">Act. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19.</note> Thus much of euill Seruants, that yee may learne what to auoide and to take heed of: now looke ye vpon ſome good
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18610:23"/> ſeruants, that yee may ſee and know what to imitate and follow. <hi>Iacob</hi> in his youth was a good ſeruant to his Maſter<note place="margin">Gen. 31. 38. 39.</note> and vncle <hi>Laban,</hi> whom he ſerued a long time, twenty yeeres together in much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, patience, affliction and tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both of body and minde: yea with all his might (as he confeſſeth in the ſixth verſe of the ſame Chapter) in the day time conſumed with heate, and in the night with froſt, euen ſo much that hee could not ſleepe. By which meanes God bleſſed <hi>Laban</hi> his Maſter, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed his cattle for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake. Yea this <hi>Iacob</hi> is a notable example and a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of a good, godly, and faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and cheefly for hauing a ſpeciall care ouer his Maſters goods and cattle: which is a principal thing to be reſpected and required in a ſeruant; for my ſeruant is to me, <hi>alter ego,</hi> another my ſelfe, and is to haue a care of my goods in mine abſence as I my ſelfe haue, and I muſt do that by my ſeruant which I can not doe by my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid heere by his owne mouth, that for the ſpace of thoſe twenty yeeres, neither his Maſters Ewes nor
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18610:23"/> Gotes did caſt their young ones, nor went ouer barren: none of his cattle pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed to him.</p>
            <p>If any were ſtolen by day, or by night, torne and deuoured of wild beaſts, hee ſupplied and made it good of his owne, which although it were more then hee was bound to doe, yet it ſhewed in him a meruelous loue to his Maſter, and what a care and deſire he had of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters profit and commodity, more then of his owne.</p>
            <p>And this was more then his Maſter did deſerue at his hands, for he dealt but hardly with him in many things. For whereas <hi>Iacob</hi> ſerued him ſeuen yeers for <hi>Rahel,</hi> he beguiled him with <hi>Lea,</hi> bleare eyed <hi>Lea,</hi> the worſe for the better. Ten times changed hee his wages, euen ſo much that if the God, whom <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſerued and feared, had not bin with him and bleſſed him, this good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Iacob</hi> had come away empty, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing little enough. Where it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that all this good ſeruice which <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> perfourmed to his Maſter <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> hee perfourmed it for verie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, that is, becauſe hee knew
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18610:24"/> that it was the duty of a ſeruant ſo to do. Heere then ſeruants may learne how to ſerue there Maſters faithfully, carefully, and conſcionably, to refuſe no paines, no labours, heate nor cold, by day nor by night: to bee carefull for their Maſters profit, ſtudious and deſirous to ſee them goe foreward and proſper in the world. And this the muſt doe howſoeuer their Maſters deale with them, and although they deſerue it not. And yet this I ſay, that if any man haue a good Seruant which doth well: if he deale not kindly and friendly with him great is his ſinne and ſhame. But howſoeuer the Maſter dealeth, let the Seruant doe wel in all things, and then looke for the reward of recompence at the Lords hands. <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.</note> the ſonne of this <hi>Iacob,</hi> was a good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant vnto the Egiptian which bought him of the Iſmacl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes. Who becauſe his Maſter loued him, and repoſed a truſt in him therefore he could by no meanes be brought to wrong him, but made a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to doe or commit any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, eſpecially to defile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage bed; for when his filthy and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Miſtreſſe did mooue, ſollicite and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18610:24"/> importune him thereunto, hee anſwered her: <hi>How can I doe this great wickedneſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 9.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo ſinne against God, it is a great wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and ſinne againſt God, and againſt my Maſter: God hath beene my good God, and the GOD of my Father</hi> Abraham, Iſaack <hi>and</hi> Iacob, <hi>my Maſter (as thou knoweſt) hath committed his houſe and all that hee hath into mine hands, and hath reſerued nothing to himſelfe, but thee onoly which art his wife, how then can I doe it? How can I doe that which is againſt the duety which I owe both to God, and to my Maſter, and alſo againſt this my reſiſting and reclaming conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many a bad ſeruant if hee meete with a Dame or a Miſtreſſe as bad as his ſelfe, will not ſay, how ſhould I doe this ſinne and wickedneſſe, but with the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates. <hi>Come let vs bee pertakers of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9.</note> 
               <hi>let vs enioy the pleaſures that are preſent, let vs leaue ſome token of pleaſure behind vs in euery place.</hi> From which wicked reſolution and vnlawfull loue, there grow and ſpring many great and grieuous ſinnes, many thefts, and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and murthers. The Dame muſt needs ſteale from her husband, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18610:25"/> her man, to feed and nouriſh in them their vnlawfull luſts, their glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, drunkenneſſe, chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toneſſe: all which without cheere and charges cannot bee maintained, but will wax cold.</p>
            <p>As for ſoule adulteries, filthy luſts, and longings one after another, and ſinne that ceaſeth not, their eyes are full of them and of nothing elſe. Moreouer by theſe euil meanes, many an honeſt and innocent man is murthered, I meane through the vnlawfull loue of the wife, as many lamentable examples, both of old and of late, yea as the priſons and galloſes can teſtifie: and all by the vices of wicked and euill diſpoſed ſeruants. <hi>Abraham</hi> had good ſeruants, one eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, who in the Scriptures is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">Gen. 24.</note> for his fidelity in ſeeking a wife for his Maſters ſonne <hi>Iſaac.</hi> Yea all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants were good and obedient, and ſuch as are not now to bee found in all the world. For when as the Lord had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to circumciſe himſelfe, his ſonne, and all the male ſeruants of his<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> houſe, whether borne in his houſe, or bought with money, that euery one
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18610:25"/> ſhould bee circumciſed, that is, haue the fore-skinne of his fleſh cut off round: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> like a good man full of faith and obedience went home preſently, and put it in execution out of hand without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay: Firſt hee circumciſed himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ninty yeeres of age and nine, then his young ſonne <hi>Iſmaell,</hi> but thirteene yeeres old: next and immediately all his ſeruants: who as the text faith, <hi>Euery one without murmuring or reſiſtance obeyed the will of God and their Maſter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 26</note> The ſelfe ſame day was <hi>Abraham</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed and <hi>Iſmaell</hi> his ſonne, and all the men of his houſe. And this (if yee marke and conſider well of it) was a verie admirable and ſtrange thing, not onely that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould ſo ſoone circumciſe and cut himſelfe, and his ſonne, of whom hee had power, but chiefely that his ſeruants would bee brought ſo quickly to ſo great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as to haue their skinnes cut in that place, and after that manner: being a thing not onely exceeding painefull, but very ſtrange and neuer before heard of, ſince the world beganne, they had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18610:26"/> no ſcriptures nor lawes ſo to command them, no examples ſo to ſhew them: and therefore their obedience was the more maruelous and commendable that they would ſo ſpeedily conforme and reſigne themſelues, and their wills to the will of God and their maiſter, in a matter of ſo great importance. I thinke if yee ſeeke all the world now ye ſhall find no ſuch Seruants: nay ye ſhall ſcant find any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects that wil do ſo much at the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of their Prince, much leſſe ſhal ye find Chriſtians which wil be ſo obedient to the will and word of the Lord their God. But what was the cauſe that theſe Seruants of <hi>Abraham</hi> were ſo tractable and willing to be ruled? <hi>Abraham</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was a good maiſter, who had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed them, and trayned them vp to this knowledge of their duty toward God and man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as himſelfe doth teſtifie for him: I know that <hi>Abraham</hi> will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand<note place="margin">Ge. 18. 19.</note> his ſonnes and his houſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him that they keepe the way of the Lotd, to doe righteouſneſſe and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nothing maketh good ſeruants ſo much as the goodneſſe of the Maſters;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18610:26"/> the better and the wiſer maiſters bee in gouerning, the better wil the ſeruants be in obeying, and ſeruing, as a wiſe man<note place="margin">Seneca</note> ſayth: <hi>melius imperanti melius paretur.</hi> In like manner the Seruants of the Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were ſo ready and willing that if their maiſter had ſayd but goe, or come, or do this, forth with they hearkned and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. How came this to paſſe? hee was a good man and a good maiſter, and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his ſeruants deare and precious vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When Ieſus</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Luke) entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 72.</note> 
               <hi>Capernaum, there was a certaine Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turions Seruant ſick which was deare vnto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One cauſe that there be now ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bad ſeruants is, that there be ſo many bad maiſters, which eſteeme not, neither make any accompt of their Seruants, but only to ſerue their owne turnes, as men do of their cattell, and not for the good of the ſeruant, but onely for their owne gaine and lucre, nay there bee many men which reſpect not their ſeruants ſo much as they doe their dogges.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18610:27"/>
            <p>I haue knowne ſome men who when they haue beene all the day abroade ſwaggering and ſwearing, hunting and whoring, when they haue come home at night would aske carefullie what their dogges had, and how they had beene ſerued, and what was prouided for them: which men I thinke verely in all their liues neuer once inquired of their ſeruants how they were vſed, or what was prouided for their ſuppers, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they had laboured neuer ſo hard all the day.</p>
            <p>And hence it is that ſeruants, for the moſt part, are ſo bad and careleſſe, and ſuch as doe not their worke for loue and for conſcience ſake as they ought to doe, but onely for feare and faſhion-ſake, with ſeruice to the eye as men-pleaſers, and to ſpeake the truth, ſeruants many times and in many places are ſo bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed that ſome of them forſake all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, giue themſelues to idleneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vagabonds, rogues and theeues. Wherefore let Maſters in the feare of<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 16</note> God learne to know and performe their parts and duties in this behalfe, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18610:27"/> to this end let them ſearch the Scriptures which are able not onely to inſtruct them, but to make them perfect. The<note place="margin">Col. 3. 22</note> ſame Scriptures which call vpon ſeruants to doe their duties toward their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; the ſame crie alſo to the Maſters to doe the like vnto their ſeruants. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had charged the ſeruants among the <hi>Colloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> to bee obedient to their Maſters in all things, ſeruing them in ſingleneſſe of heart, fearing GOD, knowing that of the Lord they ſhall receiue the reward of inheritance &amp;c. By and by he turneth his ſpeech to the Maſters ſaying: <hi>And ye Maſters doe vnto your ſeruants that which</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 1</note> 
               <hi>is iuſt and equall, knowing that yee alſo haue a Maſter in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where it is apparant that as ſeruants owe much duety to their Maſters: ſo there Maſters owe a duty to them alſo, and that is to vſe them well, and to doe nothing vnto them but that which is iuſt and meet, and beſeeming men which profeſſe piety and Chriſtianity: and this is the reaſon which the Apoſtle giueth: <hi>Becauſe they alſo haue a Maſter in heauen,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18610:28"/> beecauſe there is one common Maſter of vs all, who if Maſters doe abuſe their ſeruants and the power which they haue ouer them, hee will requite, repay, and reuenge it: as it is ſaid there by the<note place="margin">Col. 3. 25</note> Apoſtle: <hi>Hee that doth wrong, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue for the wrong which hee hath done,</hi> and there is no reſpect of perſons with GOD; the Lord will reward abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly all that doe wrong and euill, whether they bee Maſters or Seruants. Wherefore yee that bee Maſters heare this: it is your parts and duties if your ſeruants doe well, to vſe and intreate them as brethren and coheires with you of the ſame grace, and of the ſame glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: as the Lordes free-men and Chriſts<note place="margin">1. Cor 7. 22 Ioh. 15. 14</note> Seruants: as the friends of Chriſt, as Chriſts little ones, and as partakers of the benefit.</p>
            <p>That hard and cruell ſeruitude, bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and ſlauery which was vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles, which knew not God, is taken away by the law of grace, by that grace, mercy, loue and commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration which Ieſus Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our bought vs, brought vs, and taught
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18610:28"/> vs one toward another. Yea God as hee hath created vs all alike, redeemed vs all alike, and called vs all alike, ſo hee eſteemeth vs all alike. With him there is neither Iewe, nor Gentile, poore nor rich, young nor old, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter nor Seruant: but in euery Nation, in euery ſtate, calling, or degree of<note place="margin">Act. 10 34</note> men: whoſoeuer feareth him, and doth righteouſneſſe is accepted of him; and whoſoeuer doth otherwiſe ſhall receiue for the euill which hee hath done, GOD is no acceptour of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>Harken alſo what good counſell the<note place="margin">Col. 3. 25</note> wiſe man giueth you. <hi>If thou haue a faithfull ſeruant, let him bee vnto thee as thine owne ſoule, intreate and vſe him as thy brother, for thou haſt neede</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 3. 29</note> 
               <hi>of him, as of thy ſelfe;</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place hee ſaith: <hi>Whereas thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant worketh truely, intreate him not euilly &amp;c.</hi> Let thy ſoule loue a good ſeruant, and defraude him not of<note place="margin">Eccl. 7. 20</note> his liberty, neither leaue him a poore man.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Deut,</hi> alſo it is written: thou ſhalt not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18610:29"/> opreſſe the hired<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeruant that is poore and needy, neither of thy brethren nor of the ſtranger that is in thy land, within<note place="margin">Deut. 24. 14</note> thy gates: thou ſhalt giue him his hire for his day: neither ſhal the ſunne go downe vpon it, for hee is poore, and therewith ſuſtaineth his life, leaſt hee crye againſt thee vnto the Lord, and ſo thy ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine: mark firſt what is ſayd: thou ſhalt not oppreſſe a poore hired ſeruant, what is it to oppreſſe him, to denye and detaine from him his hire, his wages, for which thou hiredſt him, thou muſt not detaine<note place="margin">Eccl 34. 14</note> and keep back this from him, no not one night, the ſunne ſhall not goe downe ſo much as once vpon it, becauſe his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is that wherewith he nouriſheth and maintaineth his life. The wages of the needy is the life of the poore ſeruant; and therefore he that defraudeth him thereof taketh away his life, and ſo killeth him: take heed of this, for it followeth if hee crye againſt thee, vnto the Lord, the Lord will heare him: and then thy ſinne ſhall remaine written and regiſtred in Gods infallible knowledge: and in the booke of thine owne conſcience as a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18610:29"/> thouſand witneſſes againſt thee. So Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh to certaine euil hard-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and cruell rich men and maiſters<note place="margin">Ia. 4. 5</note> behold the bire of the Labourers which haue reaped your fieldes (which is by you kept back by fraud) cryeth, and their cryes are entred into the eares of the Lord of hoſts. Where yee may ſee and learne that it is a greeuous, and a crying ſinne, to wrong and hurt a poore hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſeruant, and a poore labouring man, and ſpecially to detaine and keepebacke from them their hire and wages.</p>
            <p>Aud yet this notwithſtanding (good Lord) it is an vſuall and common thing in euery place ſo to doe: many men haue no remorſe nor make any conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at it; but when this wages is due, and there is great reaſon that the poore man had it, hee is conſtrained to goe to a Iuſtice, and fetch a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or elſe hee is ſure to haue none there and when the maiſter hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and giuen his word before the Iuſtice to pay it, yet by your leaue for all that hee ſhall ſtay his maiſters leaſure,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18610:30"/> and come twiſe for it before he haue it, and perhappes in the end not haue it at all. Some time (it may bee) becauſe they will not of malice; Some time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot through want, and haue it not.</p>
            <p>Theſe bee horrible crying ſinnes, and the cries of them which bee thus wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (as <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith) <hi>entred into the eares of the LORD of Hoſts,</hi> that is, of the GOD of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the ſame Lord will auenge them quickly, if they crie vnto<note place="margin">Luk. 18. 8.</note> him day and night, and ſure I am that the patient abiding of the poore ſhall not bee forgotten for euer. <hi>Wherefore (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 140. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>in the LORD) let euerie man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his vocation whereunto hee is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> Art thou called to bee a Seruant? care not for it; Thinke thy ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 21</note> neuer the worſe, thy ſaluation is neuer the further from thee: onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour that thou maiſt bee found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and haue the wages of the good Seruant. Labour, ſuffer, ſerue. Labour faithfully, ſuffer patiently, obey dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlie and humbly. Grudge not at thy labour, for thereunto thou art
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18610:30"/> called. Labour is common to all men: yea Ieſus Chriſt him ſelfe made choice of a painfull and laborious life. Grudge not at thy ſeruitude, for it is Gods ordinance, and the effect of ſinne, as all the euills and miſeries of this life are: for if there had beene no ſinne, there had beene no miſery, no ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, no bondage. The Lord for a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the womans ſinne ſaid vnto her. <hi>Thou ſhalt bee vnder the power</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>of the man, and hee ſhall rule ouer thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither doe thou murmur that men beeing all of one, and the ſame Nature are ſo vnequally placed, one to rule, and another to obey: for this alſo is of GOD, euen his good ordinance, which thou maiſt not reſiſt, nor cotemne. And to this end, I meane, that thou bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſeruant maiſt performe theſe duties: pray vnto the Lord to make thee meeke and lowly, that thou maiſt bee in thine owne eies a little one, little not in ſence and vnderſtanding, but concerning all maliciouſneſſe: otherwiſe thou wilt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer humble and bow thy ſelfe to theſe good duties.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18610:31"/> For (as a wiſe man ſaith) and wee ſee it by experience, onely thoſe things, <hi>quae exilia ſunt, fllexibilia ſunt,</hi> which are ſmall and little are flexible and apt to bow, as in a twigge or rodde; looke how much more it is little, ſo much the better will it bend and bow, euen ſo a ſeruant looke how much more hee is meeke and lowly, that is, little in his owne eyes, ſo much the better hee plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſeruant, and bendeth his heart and affections to thoſe things which are required of him. When a ſeruant is proude, high-minded, and wel conceited of him ſelfe, there is no hope of him:<note place="margin">Pro. 26. 12.</note> there is more hope of a foole. There can bee no true ſeruice and obedience without humility and lowlineſſe of minde.</p>
            <p>Therefore harken what your Lord and Maſter ſaith to you, and to vs all,<note place="margin">Mat 11.</note> 
               <hi>Come learne of mee becauſe I am meeke and lowly of heart, and yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules. And now if yee know theſe things bleſſed are yee if you doe them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 13. 17</note> And that yee may the better doe and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18610:31"/> perfourme them: The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and his good ſpirit bee with you, labour with you, and remaine with you all for euer-more.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
